Guide to the Urie Bronfenbrenner papers, [ca. 1960-2011]
Bronfenbrenner, Urie papers, [ca. 1960-2011]
- Series I. Subject Files, Lecture Notes, Trip Files
  - Hungary (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Soviet Material - Pendaflex folder (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Australia (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Brazil (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Germany Demographics (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - German Lectures (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Japan - Berlin Chapters (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Australia (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Maori Socialiation (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Korea (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Japan Paper (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Japan, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Japan (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - German Texts (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Japan Socialization - Kojima (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Japan Weisz (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Japan Socialization - Yamada (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Mother-Infant: Japan (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Mother-Infant: Japan, Fagel (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Japan Info - Panda Flex folder (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - France (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - New Zealand (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Finland (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Ireland (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Hungary (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Indonesia (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - India (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Israel (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Italy (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Czechoslavakia (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Soviet Classrooms (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Turkey (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Denmark (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - German Democratic Republic (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Malaysia (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - New Zealand (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Norway (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Spain (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Tokyo (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Exchange (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Two Worlds' Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Proposal for a Series of Addresses (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - USSR Letters Outstanding (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - US-USSR Tensions Proposal (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Soviet Socialization: Statistics (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - USSR Sociology (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - USSR Anti-semitism (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - USSR Visits - Spring, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Soviet WWYD (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Switzerland (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Venezuela (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Infant Care (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Japan Mother-Infant relations (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Ethnicity - Steinberg (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Working Mother: Before 1970 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Birth Order + Sibling Ratio (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Antecedents of Achievement - Rosen (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Grandparents - Head Start, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Caldwell (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Crouter, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Attachment - Thompson (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Maternal Separation - Rheingold (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Glen Collins (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Lucille Atkin (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Parental Values: Kohl, et al. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Conformity (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Stanley Milgram (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Social Class ages 2-6 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Genetics (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Parent Child Centers (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Child Abuse Primary (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Communities Japanese (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Zinchenko (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Alienation (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Chinese Paradox (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Concepts of Development (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Theories of Personality (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Trends in School Achievement (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - School - Simmons (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Classroom Settings General (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Classroom Climates (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Family & School: Epstein (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - School Integration: Primary (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Coleman Report (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Effects of segregation & desegregation (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Children in the world of work (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Menarche (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Family Decision Making (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Adolescent Puberty (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Kandal & Lesser (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Adolescent Peer Groups, 1960-1969 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Jessor Primary (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Rutter - Notes (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Effects of Marriage (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Life Course - Moen (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Studies of Twins Reared Together (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Aging: Elder (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Baumrind, 1980-1989 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Baumrind studies (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Pulkinnen Primary (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Advisory Committee on Child Development (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Control - Discipline vs. Permissiveness (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Patterns of Child Rearing: Sears (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Childrearing & Dogs (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Changing Child in Changing Environment (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Parental Rejection and Neglect (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Maternal Overprotection (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - The Good Child & the Accepted Child (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Socialization - Baldwin et al. (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Scarr (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Prematurity (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Smoking 60's - 70's Background (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Mother-Newborn Sex Differences (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - 488 Notes - Early Sex Differences (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - 488 Notes - Neonates (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Newborn & Infancy Bee et al. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Sex Difference in Mother-Infant Interaction (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Infancy Sex Difference in Development (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Breast feeding (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Classical conditioning (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - First Year Father-Infant Interaction (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Father-Infant Interaction (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Mother-Infant Interaction (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Infant Cries - Ainsworth (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Spitz Smiling Response (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Mother-Infant Modeling (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Crockenberg Social Supports (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Mother-Infant Interactions (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Social support - Crnic (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Scarr (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Problems of Eugenics (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - LSD Chromosomal Damage (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Anomalies in Sex Chromosomes (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Problems of Eugenics (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Scientific Method - Gentry Study (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Effects of Atomic Radiation (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Specific Genetic Effects (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Sex Differences in Spatial Ability (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Problems of Inbreeding (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Anomalies in Sex Chromosomes (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Down's Syndrome (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Anomalies of Sex Chromosomes XYY (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Genetic Effects in Early Infancy (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Genetics: Magnification of Differences (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Genetics of Criminality (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Schockley's Thesis (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Genetics of Behavior: Animal Studies (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - X^2 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Analysis of Coverance (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Testing for Homogeneity in Regression (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Sums & Difference Formula (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Curvelinear Regression (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Parial Regression Method (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Analysis of Variance (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Head Start (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Paper - "Research on Parent-Child Relations and Social Policy: How to Proceed" - by Garbarino and Bronfenbrenner, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Paper - "Assessing Neighborhoods for Families" - Garbarino and Nan Crouter, no date (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Papers - "The Problem of Construct Validity in Assessing the Ecological Correlates of Child Abuse and Neglect"- Garbarino and Crouter and "The Human Ecology of Child Abuse and Neglect: The Role of Neighborhoods and the Social Networks of Families", no date (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence concerning Jim Garbarino, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence concerning Jim Garbarino, 1970-1979 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence concerning Jim Garbarino, 1970-1979 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence concerning Jim Garbarino, 1970-1979 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Boys Town - Urie Bronfenbrenner and Jim Garbarino - Correspondence and papers concerning work done at Boys Town (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - "An Empirical Study of the Roots of Alienation Among College Students" - Bronfenbrenner and Garbarino - report prepared for the Association for the Aid of Handicapped Children (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence between Sen. Fulbright and Prof. Bronfenbrenner, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Course material - Development in Context - HD 603, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Course material - Scientific Method in the Study of Human Behavior and Seminar on the Ecology of Human Development, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Course material - 690, 1976, 1977, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Course material - Groups as Socializing Agents, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Development of Human Behavior - prelims, assignments, 1969-1973 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Institute for Defense Analysis and Consultant Security Briefing, 1963 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Poverty Kill Testimony, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Dolley Madison Award given to Bronfenbrenner by the National Center for Clinical Infant Programs, 1991 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - "Bronfenbrenner's Contribution to Psychological Theory and Research: A Review and Critique" by Michele S. Reimer, 1992-12-08 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - John Clausen - Profile and Obituary, 1996 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - "The State of Some Americans" Review by Catherine Chilman of 'The State of Americans: This Generation and the Next, 1997 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Talks, 1990-1999 (Box 30, Folder 18)
  - Paper written by Urie Bronfenbrenner's student on Alexander Pushkin (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Program from the first Urie Bronfenbrenner Conference, 2007-10 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series II. Grant Files
  - "A Comparative Study of Various Project Head Start Programs" John Harding-Dept. of Child Development and Family Relationships, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - The Engelmann-Becker Program, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Annual reports - HDFS and Psychology Department, 1973-1974-1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - NIMH proposal -"The Comparative Ecology of Human Development", 1976 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Comparative Ecology of Human Development - NIE Site Visit, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - NIE Budget and site visit, 1979-1980 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - "Comparative Ecology of Human Development Project" Quarterly Report to NIE - Year II, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - "Comparative Ecology of Human Development" - Year III, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Spencer Foundation - Research, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - Spencer Foundation - "The Comparative Ecology of Human Development Project": Year Two 1982; "Stress, Social Support, and the Response to Ecological Transition by School-Aged Children", 1983-1986 (Box 13, Folder 26)
  - Carnegie Corp. - Proposal - "A Longitudinal Study of Process in the Operation of Family Support Systems", 1981 (Box 13, Folder 27)
  - Kellogg Foundation - "From the Pre-School Years Through First Grade Entry: A Plan for Statewide Application and National Dissemination of the Family Matters Experience", 1981 (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - Family Matters Film Project - proposal to Carnegie Corporation, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 29)
  - NIE- Management Plans/Activities/Deliverables, 1980-1983 (Box 13, Folder 30)
- Series III. Published Works
  - "Measurement of Sociometric Status, Structure and Development." Sociometry Monographs, No. 6. NY: Beacon House, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "Research Planning in Neuropsychiatry and Clinical Psychology in the Veterans Administration." Reprinted from Journal of Clinical Psychology, Vol. IV, No. 1, 1947-01 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "Improvisations: An Application of Psychodrama in Personality Diagnosis." University of Michigan, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "Interdisciplinary Planning for Team Research on Constructive Community Behavior." Reprinted from Human Relations, Vol. V, No. 2, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "Principles of Professional Ethics." Cornell Studies in Social Growth, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - "What Makes for Effective Citizenship?" Reprinted from Farm Research, Vol. XVIII, No. 2, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - "Personality." Reprinted from Annual Review of Psychology, Vol. 4, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - "A Method for the Analysis of Dyadic Effects in Interpersonal Perception." Prepared for the Symposium on Theory and Research in Interpersonal Perception, APA Convention, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - "The Measurement of Skill in Social Perception." Cornell Studies in Social Growth, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - "The Study of Identification Through Interpersonal Perception." Prepared for Symposium Person Perception, Harvard, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - "Socialization and Social Class Through Time and Space." Published in Maccoby, New-comb and Hartley, Readings in Social Psychology. New York: Henry Holt and Co., 1958 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Past Reviews, 1979-1981 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - "Family Authority Structure and Child Behavior." Study performed by Profs. Bronfenbrenner and Devereux at Cologne and Schleswig-Holstein, Germany, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - "An Achievement Creates a Need." Review of John W. Atkinson, ed., published in Contemporary Psychology, Vol. V, No. 3 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - "Personality and Participation." In Journal of Social Issues, Vol XVI, No. 4, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - "The Changing American Child." In the Merrill-Palmer Quarterly, Vol. 7, No. 2, April 1961, and in Values and Ideals of American Youth, ed. Eli Ginzberg, 1961. Presented at the Golden Anniversary White House Conference on Children and Youth, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Other Articles and Reviews, before 1960, no date (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - "Appraisal of Personality Characteristics in Children." From Handbook of Re-search Methods in Childhood Development, John Wiley and Sons, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - "Some Problems in Communicating with Americans about the Soviet Union." Cornell University, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - "Toward a Social Ecology of Childhood Accidents." Review of academic papers, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - "Some Familial Antecedents of Responsibility and Leadership in Adolescence." Cornell University, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - "Preliminary Summary Report of Observations as a Member of the U.S. Medical Ecology Mission to the USSR", 1961 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - "The Mirror Image in Soviet-American Relations: A Social Psychologist's Report." In The Soviet System in Theory and Practice, ed. Harry G. Schaffer. NY: Meredith Publishing, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - "Mirror Image," revised and updated edition, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - "Soviet Studies of Personality Development and Socialization." Reprinted from Some Views on Soviet Psychology, APA, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - "Secrecy: A Basic Tenet of the Soviets." In the New York Times Magazine, 1962-04-22 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - "Soviet Methods of Character Education: Some Implications for Research.", 1962 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - "Patterns of Parent Behavior in the United States of America and the Federal Republic of West Germany: A Cross-National Comparison." Cornell University, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - "Some Possible Effects of a Large-Scale American Shelter Program on the Soviet Union and Other Nations." Submitted to the Armed Services Committee of the House of Representatives, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - "The Role of Age, Sex, Class, and Culture in Studies of Moral Development." Cornell University, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - "Toward a Theoretical Model for the Analysis of Parent-Child Relationships in a Social Context." Reprinted from Parental Attitudes and Child Behavior. Springfield, IL: Charles C. Thomas, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - "The Incest Taboo and the Mating Patterns of Animals." Published in American Anthropologist, April 1963. Reprinted in Readings in Introductory Sociology, eds. Gracey and Wrong, Macmillan, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - "Why Do the Russians Plant Trees Along the Road?" Saturday Review, 1963-01-05 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - "Upbringing in Collective Settings in Switzerland and the USSR: An Interim Report.", 1964 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - "Psychology as a Core Discipline in Home Economics." Department of Child and Family Relationships, NYS College of Home Economics, Cornell University, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - "Allowing for Soviet Perceptions and Motives." Cornell University, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - "A Report of Institutional Methods of Upbringing in the USSR" Cornell University, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - "The Needs of America's Children." Cornell University, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - "The National Need for Research on Factors Affecting Human Development." Prepared for Sub-Committee on Labor and Public Welfare, US House of Representatives, 1966-03-22 (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - "Institutional Approaches to Cultural Deprivation--American and Soviet." Prepared for Third International Scientific Symposium on Mental Retardation. Boston, MA, 1966-04-11 (Box 9, Folder 40)
  - "Cross-Cultural Studies of Child Rearing." Cornell University, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 41)
  - "The Split Society: Children vs. Adults." Cornell University, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 42)
  - "Response to Pressure from Peers vs. Adults Among Soviet and American Schoolchildren."Presented at American Sociological Association in Miami, Florida and at the Symposium on Factors in Personality Development, at the 19th International Congress of Psychology, Moscow, USSR, 1966-08 (Box 9, Folder 43)
  - "The Psychological Cost of Quality and Equality in Education." Reprinted in International Journal of Psychology, Vol. 2, No. 3, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 44)
  - "Makarenko and the Collective Family." Preface to Makarenko's Book for Parents, pub. in USA as The Collective Family. NY: Doubleday, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 45)
  - "When is Infant Stimulation Effective?" Published in Environmental Influences. NY: Rockefeller University Press, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 46)
  - "Standards of Social Behavior in Four Cultures." Published in International Journal of Psychology, Vol.3, No. 1, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 47)
  - "Implications of Follow-Through Programs for the American School System." In Poverty and Human Resources Abstracts, Vol. III, No. 4. "Motivational and Social Components in Compensatory Education Programs: Suggested Principles, Practices and Research Designs." Cornell University, 1968-07-1968-08 (Box 9, Folder 48)
  - "Soviet Methods of Upbringing and their Effects." Cornell University, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - "On the Making of the New Man: Soviet vs. American." Cornell University, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 50)
  - "Effects of Social Intervention on Psychological Development." Cornell University, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 51)
  - "Early Deprivation of Animals: a Cross-Species Analysis." In Early Experience and Behavior: The Psychobiology of Development. Springfield: Charles C. Thomas, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 52)
  - "The Changing Soviet Family." Cornell University, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - "On the Making of New Men." Condensed and revised from "On the Making of the New Man;" printed in Canadian Journal of Behavioral Science, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 54)
  - Reviews of Bruno Bettelheim's The Children of the Dream, Macmillan, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - "Damping the Unemployability Explosion." Saturday Review, 1969-01-04 (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - "Child-Rearing in England and the United States: A Cross-National Comparison." Published in the Journal of Marriage and the Family, 1969-04 (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - "Social Factors in Personality Development." Hebrew translation, the Henrietta SzoldInstitute, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 58)
  - "Motivational and Social Components in Follow-Through Programs: Suggested Principles, Practices, and Research Designs." Cornell University, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - "A Statement on the Comprehensive Preschool Education and Child Care Act." Testimony offered before the Committee on Education and Labor, U.S. House of Representatives, 1969-12-02 (Box 9, Folder 60)
  - "Some Reflections on 'Antecedents of Optimal Psychological Adjustment'." Published in the Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - "The Dependency Drive as a Factor in Infant Learning and Development." Published in the Swiss Journal of Pure and Applied Psychology, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 62)
  - "Czynniki Spoleczne W Rozwoju Osobowosci." Published in Psychologia WychowawczaDwumiesiecznik (USSR), Vol. XIII, No. 1, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 63)
  - "Children and Parents." Cornell University, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - "Reaction to Social Pressure from Adults vs. Peers Among Soviet Day School and Boarding School Pupils in the Perspective of an American Sample." Published in the Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, Vol. 15, No. 3, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - "Bronfenbrenner's Moral Dilemmas in Britain: Children, Their Peers and their Parents."Beloff and Paton, University of Edinburgh, Scotland, UK. Published in International Journal of Psychology, Vol. 5, No. 1, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - "Autonomy and Conformity in Response to Pressure from Peers and Adults in Icelandic School Children." Biemiller and Day, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - "Authority and Moral Development Among German and American Children: A Cross-National Pilot Experiment." Reprinted from the Journal of Comparative Family Studies,Vol. III, No. 1, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - A Letter from the International Study Group, (1970) (Box 9, Folder 69)
  - "The Roots of Alienation." Cornell University, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 70)
  - "Recreating Human Ecology." Address at the Human Ecology Symposium, "Human Ecology: The Next Ten Years." Cornell University, Ithaca, New York, 1979-11-10 (Box 9, Folder 71)
  - Regarding Two Worlds of Childhood: U.S. and USSR Published Russell Sage Foundation, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 72)
  - Two Worlds, before revision, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 73)
  - "Social Factors in Personality Development." Polish edition, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - "Day Care USA." Statement prepared at the request of Edward F. Zigler, Director, Office of Child Development (U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare), 1970 (Box 9, Folder 75)
  - "Does Technology Mechanize Man? An Experiment on Live vs. Televised Education."Cornell University, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 76)
  - Preface for the English translation of "The Psychology of Preschool Children," Zaporozhets and Elkonin, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 77)
  - "Adaptation of Brofenbrenner's Moral Dilemmas Test: A Cross-Culture Study.", 1971 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - "Changes in Parental Behavior Reported by Children in West Germany and the United States.", 1971 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - "Day Care USA: A Statement of Principles.", 1971 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Reprinted in the Peabody Journal of Education
  - Driezehnjahrige Schweizer Zwischen Peers und Erwachsenen im Interkulturelien Vergleich.", 1971 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - "On Making Human Beings Human.", 1971 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "Personality and Response to Pressure from Peer vs. Adults", 1971 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "A Place to Meet, a Way to Understand.", 1971 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Statement to Sub-Committee on Children and Youth of the United States, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Washington D.C., White House Conference on Children
  - Strumilin Affair, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - "Television as a Constructive Force in the Lives of Children and Families.", 1971 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    Cornell University
  - "Who Cares for America's Children?", 1970-11-18 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    Address at the Conference of the National Association for the Education of Young Children, Boston, MA
  - "Umwelt und Aggression.", 1971-07-1971-08 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    In Neue Sammlung
  - "Who Stands en Loco Parentis?", 1971 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Child Development Act, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - "College Students in the 70's: Alienation vs. Idealism.", 1972 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - "Early Deprivation in Monkey and Man", 1972 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - "Is 80% of Intelligence Genetically Determined?", 1972 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - "The President and the Children.", 1972 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Regarding "Child Care or Family-Elimination?", 1972 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - SDS Affair, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 20)